Guide to the Yale University Divinity School Memorabilia Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
Yale University Divinity School Memorabilia Collection
1701-2018
RG 53
Yale University Divinity School Library
50+
100+ boxes
This collection represents primarily non-official documentation of life at Yale Divinity School. The official archives of the Yale University Divinity School are housed at Sterling Memorial Library. The Yale University Divinity School was formed as a separate department of the University in 1822. Since 1972 Berkeley Divinity School has been affiliated with Yale University Divinity School. The Institute of Sacred Music, founded at Yale in 1973, is also affiliated with the Divinity School.
Yale University. Divinity School
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Associated Materials
The following faculty members and deans have separate individual record groups:
Sydney Ahlstrom, RG 83
Roland H. Bainton, RG 75
Harlan P. Beach, RG 60
Charles Reynolds Brown, RG 37
Millar Burrows, RG 71
James Dittes, RG 174
Eleazar Thompson Fitch, RG 93
Kenneth Scott Latourette, RG 3
George Lindbeck, RG 172
Douglas Clyde Macintosh, RG 50
Randolph C. Miller, RG 173
Raymond P. Morris, RG 80
Liston Pope, RG 49
Marvin Pope, RG 135
Frank Chamberlin Porter, RG 119
Frank Knight Sanders, RG 122
Clarence Prouty Shedd, RG 35
Henry Hallam Tweedy, RG 131
Paul Vieth, RG 59
Williston Walker, RG 51
The following faculty members are included in Record Group No. 30, Miscellaneous Personal Papers:
John Clark Archer
Benjamin Wisner Bacon
Robert Calhoun
Edward Lewis Curtis
George Park Fisher
Samuel Harris
Hugh Hartshorne
James Mason Hoppin
Paul Schubert
George Barker Stevens
Charles Cutler Torrey
Berkeley Divinity School records, RG 216 comprises the official archives of the BDS at Yale Divinity School; one box of duplicate ephereral material is available in RG 53, Series XI for purposes of ready-reference.
Official archives of the Yale Divinity School Library may be found in RG 92.
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1701, Yale College was a place "wherein Youth through the blessing of Almighty God may be fitted for Publick employment both in Church and Civil State." In 1822 the Divinity School became a separate school within the University and now is one of eleven graduate and professional schools, which, with the College, comprise Yale University. Yale University Divinity School provides three degree programs: the Master of Divinity, the Master of Arts in Religion, and the Master of Sacred Theology.
Since 1971, Berkeley Divinity School, an Episcopal seminary, has been affiliated with Yale University Divinity School. Berkeley Divinity School at Yale retains its identity through its continuing board of trustees, its dean, and the Berkeley Center. Episcopal students come under the care of the Dean of Berkeley Divinity School at Yale for spiritual formation and counseling, but are not differentiated from other Yale University Divinity School students.
The Institute of Sacred Music, founded in 1973, is a center for graduate and professional students and for faculty dedicated to the interdisciplinary study of liturgy and the liturgical arts. It exists in relationship to both the Yale University Divinity School and the Yale School of Music. The Institute's primary focus is the training of musicians with vocations to the churches, particularly in organ performance and in choral conducting.
The following individuals have served as Dean of the Divinity School:
1888-1895 George Edward Day
1895-1901 George Park Fisher
1901-1905 Frank Knight Sanders
1905-1911* Edward Lewis Curtis (Acting Dean)
1911-1928 Charles Reynolds Brown
1928-1949 Luther Allan Weigle
1949-1962 Liston Pope
1961-1963* Charles William Forman (Acting Dean)
1963-1969 Robert Clyde Johnson
1969-1979 Colin Wilbur Williams
1979-1989 Leander E. Keck
1989-1990* Aidan Kavanagh (Acting Dean)
1990-1996 Thomas W. Ogletree
1996-2000 Richard Wood
2000-2001* Harry Baker Adams (Acting Dean)
2001-2002 Rebecca S. Chopp
2002-2012 Harold Attridge
2013- Gregory E. Sterling
Scope and Contents
The official archives of the Divinity School are housed at Yale University's Sterling Memorial Library. This collection represents primarily non-official documentation of life at the Divinity School, with some material documenting university-wide student religious organizations and activities.
Series I, Material Regarding Faculty, contains biographical and ephemeral material arranged alphabetically by faculty name, followed by folders that contain compilations of biographical information about Divinity School faculty members. There are no individual folders in Record Group 53 for faculty members whose personal papers are contained in Record Group No. 30, Miscellaneous Personal Papers, or in a separate manuscript group. Writings of faculty members are located with their personal papers (when separate collections exist) or in Record Group No. 27, Yale Faculty Publications and Writings. See Related Archival Materials for more information.
Series II, Material Regarding Alumni/ae, is arranged chronologically by year of the class. This material contains class lists, letters, and other news of Yale Divinity School alumni/ae. Following the chronological folders are some topical folders: Yale alumni in foreign missions, 1701-1921, Methodist YDS graduates, 1930-1959; Occupational statistics of early Yale College graduates; Ph.D.s in field of religion, 1930-1960; Wisconsin Association of YDS alumni minute-book, 1900-1934.
Series III, Material Documenting Life at YDS, contains miscellaneous printed material related to the life of Yale Divinity School. Whenever possible, contents of individual folders have been listed; however, the folder description is not exhaustive. The folders often contain several items, including correspondence, commencement and symposium programs, handbooks, information about entering students, and newspaper articles referring to YDS. Programs from important anniversaries of the school can be found in the folders corresponding with the year of the event. Also included, when available, are course listings and syllabi. The first part of this series consists of chronologically arranged documents from 1835 until the present. Following the dated material are several folders of material grouped by topic. Some topics are arranged chronologically, while some material is not dated.
Series IV, YDS Publications, Yale Divinity School publications including annual bulletins, student directories, and the alumni publication Spectrum. The publication from the Institute of Sacred Music, Prism, is located in this series as well as the journal of opinion produced by the YDS faculty, Reflection, which has been published since 1965 and was renamed Reflections in 1986.
There are several opinion journals produced during various years by students. These vary in length and format but seem to have a constant presence at the Divinity School since 1950. Some of the opinion journals include, "In Context", produced in the 1950s; "Signs and Times of Yale Divinity School", an "unofficial" publication produced from 1960-1965; "The Limb", published from the mid-1960s until 1970; "Eschatology Today", published 1977-1978; "Holy Smoke", from 1978-1980; and "Dear Theophilus", printed from 1983 until the present. Shibboleth is a student publication of creativity.
Some publications have gone through format change while some have changed their names over the years. For instance, the Yale Divinity News is a continuation of Yale Divinity Quarterly and most recently, the publication formerly known as "The Dial", is now the "Q-Source". This series also includes some wider university publications when the articles deal with Divinity related news.
Series V, Audio-Visual Materials, contains photographs,audiotapes, and videotapes. Photographs of Yale, the Divinity School and of faculty, alumni, and students are alphabetically arranged by the following topics: Alumni, Buildings/Grounds, Faculty/Staff, Students, Special Subjects and Negatives/Contact Prints. Large panoramic photographs of various classes are located in oversize folders. The audio tapes and compact discs are available for some faculty lectures and other special lectures including those given during the annual Convocation. CDs of Convocation lectures are now available for purchase from the Yale Divinity School Bookstore.
Series VI, Material Regarding Women at YDS, highlights over sixty years of women admitted to degree programs at YDS. There are studies conducted on women at YDS from various years. A lengthy oral history project consisting of taped interviews and written transcripts is also included in Series VI. The binder from the history project has been placed in an oversize box. From that project, the collection includes audio cassettes, correspondence and a file folder for each of the women interviewed - alumni, students, faculty and staff. Records and minutes of the Divinity Wives Organization which later turned into the Crescent Community are stored in this series, as well as a collection of articles regarding women's ordination and women at theological schools. Copies of Reflection with articles pertaining to women have been cross-referenced here. Finally, there are individual folders with historical information about women's speakers series and women's ministry at YDS.
Series VII contains documentation of the Gay, Lesbian, Straight, Bisexual Coalition at YDS. The material in this series comes from the efforts of the Gay, Lesbian, Straight, Bisexual Coalition (commonly referred to as "the Coalition") to document the presence of gay and lesbian persons at Yale Divinity School, and the history of the Coalition itself as a symbol of the struggles of gay and lesbian persons within the Divinity School, the Church, and the world. The collection was developed as a group project through Professor Letty Russell's class "Readings in Liberation Theologies: Gay and Lesbian Liberation Theologies."
The material is organized first according to the chronology of Coalition events and consists primarily of posters, flyers, newsletters, budget records, photos, and some correspondence. Following this material are various writings from the students and faculty of YDS pertaining to issues of gay and lesbian persons in the Church. All members of the community were asked to reflect upon the presence of the Coalition and how it has affected their semesters at YDS; the folder of "Student Reflections" contains the responses received from current and past students. The folders containing "Student Papers" represent a sample of the kinds of research and work that some students have completed as part of their degree programs. There is also a cassette tape entitled "God and Other Unanswerable Questions" by Doug Shontz (Div '98), submitted as his main contribution to the collection. The faculty papers represent some of the opinions of the YDS faculty as they have been made known both at YDS, through campus mailings and memos, and in other communities, through publication. The "Dear Theo's" found in this series are only those issues that specifically pertain to the work of the Coalition. Other "Dear Theo's" can be found in the YDS Publications series.
Series VII also contains various collected material of relevance to the Coalition. Most of this material was kept and passed down by Coalition student leaders. This material has been arranged alphabetically by material type: bibliographies and catalogues, clippings, pamphlets and articles, related organizations, and worship and educational material. The "Related Organizations" folder contains invitations, posters, and information about activities and organizations at Yale University and outside Yale which are of interest/relevance to the Coalition.
While it is not clear exactly when the Coalition began, we know of a group called the "Gay/Straight Coalition" existing from at least 1985. The group later became the "Gay/Lesbian/Straight Coalition" and, in Fall 1993, the "Gay, Lesbian, Straight, Bisexual Coalition."
Series VIII, Save the Quad, contains documentation of the controversies surrounding the deterioration of the Yale Divinity School campus buildings and the various methods for addressing the problem (e.g. relocate, renovate, rebuild). The initial discussions began as early as 1996. After a long process, it was decided to do a renovation based on the principle of "adaptive re-use". The renovation of SDQ was ultimately completed in 2003.
Series IX. Marquand Chapel, contains chapel programs and announcements arranged chronologically, dating 2000-2012.
Series X. Institute of Sacred Music, is a sampling of printed material relating to ISM events. For more information, contact the ISM directly.
Series XI. Berkeley Divinity School, is one box containing a sampling of duplicate ephermeral material, for purposes of ready reference.
Arrangement
I. Faculty
II. Alumni/ae
III. Life at YDS
IV. YDS Publications and Lectures
V. Audio Visual Material
VI. Women at YDS
VII. Gay, Lesbian, Straight, Bisexual Coalition
VIII. Save the Quad
IX. Marquand Chapel
X. Institute of Sacred Music
XI. Berkeley Divinity School
Religious education -- Connecticut; Theology -- Study and teaching -- Connecticut; Yale University. Divinity School
- Faculty, Series I; 1; Series I, Material Regarding Faculty, contains biographical and ephemeral material arranged alphabetically by faculty name, followed by folders that contain compilations of biographical information about Divinity School faculty members. There are no individual folders in Record Group 53 for faculty members whose personal papers are contained in a separate manuscript group. [See Related Archival Materials for more information.]
  Related Materials
  The following faculty members and deans have separate individual record groups: Sydney Ahlstrom, RG 83 Roland H. Bainton, RG 75 Harlan P. Beach, RG 60 Charles Reynolds Brown, RG 37 Millar Burrows, RG 71 James Dittes, RG 174 Eleazar Thompson Fitch, RG 93 Kenneth Scott Latourette, RG 3 George Lindbeck, RG 172 Douglas Clyde Macintosh, RG 50 Randolph C. Miller, RG 173 Raymond P. Morris, RG 80 Liston Pope, RG 49 Marvin Pope, RG 135 Frank Chamberlin Porter, RG 119 Frank Knight Sanders, RG 122 Clarence Prouty Shedd, RG 35 Henry Hallam Tweedy, RG 131 Paul Vieth, RG 59 Williston Walker, RG 51
  The following faculty members are included in Record Group No. 30, Miscellaneous Personal Papers: John Clark Archer Benjamin Wisner Bacon Robert Calhoun Edward Lewis Curtis George Park Fisher Samuel Harris Hugh Hartshorne James Mason Hoppin Paul Schubert George Barker Stevens Charles Cutler Torrey
  Writings of faculty members are located with their personal papers (when separate collections exist) or in Record Group No. 27, Yale Faculty Publications and Writings
  - A-F
    - Attridge, Harold W. (Box I-1)
    - Bainton, Roland (Box I-1)
    - Barr, Browne, 1953, 1955, n.d. (Box I-1)
    - Blair, Tony (Box I-1)
    - Bollier, John A. (Box I-1)
    - Brastow, Lewis Orsmond (Box I-1)
    - Calhoun, Robert L. (Box I-1)
    - Carr, Aute, 1956 (Box I-1)
    - Childs, Brevard (Box I-1)
    - Clark, Charles H. (Box I-1)
    - Cook, John W. (Box I-1)
    - Craig, Clarence T., 1945, 1946 (Box I-1)
    - Dahl, George (Box I-1)
    - Dana, Malcolm (Box I-1)
    - Davis, Ellen F., 1996 (Box I-1)
    - Davis, Jerome (Box I-1)
    - Dittes, James (Box I-1)
    - Dobihal, Edward F. (Box I-1)
    - Farley, Margaret, 1986 (Box I-1)
    - Fitch, Eleazar T. (Box I-1)
    - Franklin, R. William (12th Dean, BDS, 1998) (Box I-1)
  - G-L
    - Gibbs, Josiah Willard (Box I-1)
    - Goodrich, Chauncey Allen (Box I-1)
    - Greer, Rowan, 1989 (Box I-1)
    - Gustafson, James M., 1963 (Box I-1)
    - Harris Samuel (Box I-1)
    - Hartshorne, Hugh (Box I-1)
    - Hartt, Julian, 1944, 1953 (Box I-1)
    - Hein, Norvin, 1986-1987 (Box I-1)
    - Hicks, R. Lansing (Box I-1)
    - Holmer, Paul L., 1988 (Box I-1)
    - Huebner, Dwayne E., 1994 (Box I-1)
    - Johnson, Robert C., 1968 (Box I-1)
    - Jones, Serene (Box I-1)
    - Kavanagh, Aidan, 1989, 1994 (Box I-1)
    - Keck, Leander E., 1980 (Box I-1)
    - Kelsey, David (Box I-1)
    - Kirkham, Donald Henry, 1996 (Box I-1)
    - Kittel, Bonnie (Box I-1)
    - Kraeling, Carl H. (Box I-1)
    - Latourette, Kenneth Scott (Box I-1)
    - Lovett, A. Sidney (Box I-1)
    - Luccock, Halford E. (Box I-1)
  - M-R
    - MacDougall, Detra (Registrar, 1963-2008 (Box I-1)
    - MacGowan, Andrew (Dean, BDS, 2014- ) (Box I-1)
    - MacLennan, David A., 1949, 1954 (Box I-1)
    - Malherbe, Abraham J., 1994 (Box I-1)
    - Marshall, Paul Victor, 1996 (Box I-1)
    - Michaelsen, Robert S., 1953 (Box I-1)
    - Miller, Randolph C. (Box I-1)
    - Miller, William Lee (Box I-1)
    - Minear, Paul (Box I-1)
    - Muehl, Ernest W. (Box I-1)
    - Napier, B. Davie (Box I-1)
    - Nelson, John Oliver (Box I-1)
    - Niebuhr, H. Richard (Box I-1)
    - Nouwen, Henri J. M. (Box I-1)
    - Noyce, Gaylord B., 1994 (Box I-1)
    - Ogletree, Thomas (Box I-1)
    - Outka, Gene (Box I-1)
    - Outler, Albert C., 1947 (Box I-1)
    - Pelikan, Jaroslav J. (Box I-1)
    - Rowthorn, Jeffery (Box I-1)
    - Russell, Letty (Box I-1)
  - S-W
    - Sanneh, Lamin (Box I-1)
    - Schattauer, Thomas H., 1996 (Box I-1)
    - Schroeder, John C. (Box I-1)
    - Smith, Robert S., 1930-1931, 1935-36 (Box I-1)
    - Sterling, Gregory E. (Dean, 2012- ) (Box I-1)
    - Stout, Harry S. (Box I-1)
    - Streets, Frederick (Jerry) (Box I-1)
    - Taylor, Nathaniel W. (Box I-1)
    - Turner, Phillip W., 1991 (Box I-1)
    - Weigle, Luther (Box I-1)
    - Williams, Colin W. (Box I-1)
    - Winchester, Benjamin S. (Box I-1)
    - Wood, Richard J., 2000 (Box I-1)
    - Woodward, Ralph (Box I-1)
- Alumni/ae, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  Series II, Material Regarding Alumni/ae, is arranged chronologically by year of the class. This material contains class lists, letters, and other news of Yale Divinity School alumni/ae. Following the chronological folders are some topical folders: Yale alumni in foreign missions, 1701-1921, Methodist YDS graduates, 1930-1959; Occupational statistics of early Yale College graduates; Ph.D.s in field of religion, 1930-1960; Wisconsin Association of YDS alumni minute-book, 1900-1934.
  - General
    - Alumni Council/Alumnal Board, 1932-1969; 0.5 (Box II-1)
      Correspondence & meetings
    - Yale Alumni Fund pledges, 1924-1988; 0.5 (Box II-2)
  - Topical / Statistical information, 0.5
    - Yale Alumni in Foreign Missions, 1701-1921 (Box II-3)
    - Missionary Graduates of Yale (Box II-3)
    - Methodist BD Graduates of YDS, 1930-1959 (Box II-3)
    - Occupational Statistics of Yale Graduates (Box II-3)
    - Ph.D's in Religion (Box II-3)
    - Wisconsin Alumni Minutes, 1900-1934 (Box II-3)
    - YDS Alumni by State/Country, 1997-2005 (Box II-3a)
  - Chronologically by class
    - Class of 1819-1935 (Box II-4)
    - Class of 1936-1939 (Box II-5)
      includes Jack A. Davis (Class of 1936) "Our Life at Yale" (1977)
    - Class of 1940 (Box II-6)
      Includes: Hodges, Graham R. "The Age of Giants" Hodges, Graham, "Gleanings: The Ultimate Scrapebook" Hodges, Graham, Correspondence Hodges, Graham and Elsie, "Remembrances of Ages Past" (1997) Hodges, Graham, "H. Richard Niebuhr: Students' Recollections" (1997) Hodges, Graham, YDS Photo Album Project Hanan, Ben, "My Journey" Martin Jr., James L.: Autobiography Nelson, T. Robert: Photo album
    - Class of 1941-1951 (Box II-7)
      includes: writings by Kenneth G. Peterson (1949): "University of California Library at Berkeley, 1900-1945" (1970) "As Dad remembers people, places events and stories about the family" (1995)
    - Class of 1952 (Box II-8-A)
    - Class of 1952 (Box II-8-B)
      Leonard W. Frey (hood, gown, personal items - deposited following death 2009 Apr 6)
    - Class of 1952 (Box II-8-C)
      incl. 50th Reunion (2002) & 60th Reunion (2012)
    - Class of 1953-1997 (Box II-9)
      (incl. material re death of Sam Todd, Class of 1984)
    - Class of 2000-present (Box II-10)
- Life at YDS, Series III
  Series III, Material Documenting Life at YDS, contains miscellaneous printed material related to the life of Yale Divinity School. Whenever possible, contents of individual folders have been listed; however, the folder description is not exhaustive. The folders often contain several items, including correspondence, commencement and symposium programs, handbooks, information about entering students, and newspaper articles referring to YDS. Programs from important anniversaries of the school can be found in the folders corresponding with the year of the event. Also included, when available, are course listings and syllabi.
  Arrangement
  Chronological file consists of material arranged by date from 1835 to the present. Subject file contains material grouped by topic and arranged alphabetically.
  - Chronological file
    - 1835-1899
      - Views on Theology, 1835 (Box III-1)
      - Triennial catalogue, 1841 (Box III-1)
      - Anniversary of the Theological Department, 1842 (Box III-1)
      - Ordination of Theodore Dwight Woolsey; Valedictory Oration, 1846, 1847 (Box III-1)
      - Poem and Valedictory Oration, 1849 (Box III-1)
      - Discourse to Alumni, 1860 (Box III-1)
      - Obituary Record of Graduates (Yale College), 1865 (Box III-1)
      - Commemorative Celebration, 1866 (Box III-1)
      - Scientific Address, 1867 (Box III-1)
      - Laying of the Cornerstone of Divinity Hall; Origin of the Theological School; Yale College in 1869 (Box III-1)
      - Address at the inauguration of President Noah Porter, 1871 (Box III-1)
      - Semi-Centennial Anniversary of the Divinity School, 1872 (Box III-1)
      - Obituary Record (Yale College), 1874 (Box III-1)
      - Anniversary Exercises, 1875-1881 (Box III-1)
      - Yale College in 1876 (Box III-1)
      - The Founding of Yale College, Governor Elihu Yale, 1882 (Box III-1)
      - Yale Divinity School 1822-1888; Fourth Annual Reunion, 1888-1889 (Box III-1)
      - Admission Application - n.d.; Yale College in 1890 (Box III-1)
      - Foreign Mission Library Catalogues; Anniversary Exercises, 1892-1893 (Box III-1)
      - Foreign Mission Library Catalogues, 1894-1899 (Box III-1)
    - 1900-1955
      - Two Hundredth Anniversary of the Birth of Jonathan Edwards, 1903 (Box III-2)
      - Yale Alumni Weekly - "Broadening Divinity School", 1907 (Box III-2)
      - Unwritten Annals; Yale University Christian Association, 1909-1910 (Box III-2)
      - Yale Alumni Weekly - "The New Divinity School", 1912 (Box III-2)
      - Various articles, pamphlets, 1915-1916 (Box III-2)
      - School of Religion; Use of Liquor Manual, Department of Religious Education; Courses of Instruction Booklet, 1917-1918 (Box III-2)
      - 97th Anniversary of the School of Religion, 1919 (Box III-2)
      - 98th Anniversary of the Yale Divinity School, 1920 (Box III-2)
      - Proposal for "new" Divinity School (signed by C.R. Brown, E. Hershey Sneath, Williston Walker, B.W. Bacon), ca. 1921 (Box III-2)
      - 100th Anniversary of Yale Divinity School - programs, articles, 1921-1922 (Box III-2)
      - 101st Anniversary, 1923 (Box III-2)
      - Suggested Readings Compiled by YDS Faculty, 1925 (Box III-2)
      - Needs of the Divinity School, by C.R. Brown (Yale Alumni Weekly), 1925 Feb 27 (Box III-2)
      - YDS Department of Missions, 1926 (Box III-2)
      - Pamphlets and Paper to Faculty Wives, 1927 (Box III-2)
      - Report of Dean Weigle; 105th Anniversary, 1928 (Box III-2)
      - Department of Religious Education, Yale's Institute of Human Relations, 1929 (Box III-2)
      - Articles About Prospect Street; Dean's Report; Commencement, 1931 (Box III-2)
      - "Whither the Negro Church?" Seminar at YDS, 1931 Apr 13-15 (Box III-2)